PANDIYAN MUTHURAMAN

Contact No.: +91-9600963436

Email-id : maestropandy@gmail.com



Professional Summary

5+ years of experience as a Cloud Engineer, Operation and System Administration Engineer supporting Cloud Infrastructure Openstack, AWS. DevOps with strong background on configuration management, CI/CD, infra automation, databases, Orchestrating container platform with Kubernetes. Design and Implement end-to-end IAAS. Strong Exposure to handle large scale cloud setup.

Employment History

Employer: Reliance Jio Infocomm, Bangalore

Project Name: JKAAS (Sep 2018- Present)

Description: Deliver Kubernetes as a service like K8s Cluster, Logging, Monitoring, Gitlab, CI/CD, Backup

Kubernetes cluster

Environment: Kubernetes - Container Orchestration Platform

Responsibilities:

- Designing and Deploying scalable, HA Kubernetes cluster on Openstack, Baremetal and AWS Platform using Terraform, Ansible
- Deployed Kubernetes cluster setup of Multi-Master, Load Balancer, Ingress, Ceph Storage with SSO Implemented.
- Delivered end-to-end service on Kubernetes including Monitoring with Prometheus, Logging with ELK/Loki and Multi-tenancy with helm.
- Delivered dedicated Gitlab as a service to each project users separated by Namespace to deploy application from CI/CD pipelines on Kubernetes setup
- Delivered Kubernetes Cluster, PV backup and restore solutions using heptio Velero software.
- Implemented, Integrated Storage solution with Openstack cinder and ceph with rook

Project Name: JAWS Engineering (Oct 2017 - Aug 2018)

Description: Deliver DevOps as a service like Backup, Monitoring, Database, IAM, DNS and Billing as a

service

Environment: Openstack Cloud platform

Responsibilities:

- Delivered Database as a service for MongoDB, MariaDB, MSSQL database using heat template
- Delivered DNS as a service for users to create A/CNAME records backed by powerdns in backend running on Kubernetes
- Delivered Backup as a service using BackupNinja, Xtrabackup, Innobackupex tools to backup database MySQL, PostgreSQL, Cassandra

- Delivered Monitoring as a service using Monasca openstack components for tenant level monitoring in Kubernetes setup & Docker swarm
- Delivered Billing as a service using Monasca metrics and generated bill for resource usage

Project Name: JAWS Operation

Environment: Openstack Cloud Platform (Feb 2016- Sep 2017)

Description: Deploy and Manage Openstack Control Plane using Mirantis Drivetrain & Fuel with Multi-site

environment holding 400+ Nodes setup

Responsibilities:

- Deploy & Manage large openstack cloud platforms and their dependencies in HA mode
- Deploy and verifying Physical nodes, APT node & Salt setup for deploying drivetrain.
- Add custom commissioning scripts in saltstack to increase service performance
- Deploy Stacklight LMA components for capacity planning, operational health and monitoring
- Integrated Jenkins Job configuration history with slack channel to capture actions.
- Verifying and Validating a new salt formula by running invalid YAML, Salt state.
- Managing compute, gateway nodes like adding, reprovision and remove.
- Managing NGINX, HAProxy, Apache, RabbitMQ and Gallera Certificates.
- Performed Ironic baremetal provisioning by preparing special images, configure and enrolling baremetal into Ironic, and add required compute flavors.
- Restrict VM Image policy to allow specific roles to perform actions.
- Preparing light weight customised images and upload into glance
- Performed Ceph operations like add, remove Monitor, OSD, RADOS Gateway Node.
- Performed Ceph backup and restore during maintenance window.
- Troubleshooting openstack services like Nova, Glance, Keystone and Cinder
- Performed Monitoring, Metering, and collected resource usage using ceilometer.
- Monitor, Maintenance of failure compute and storage nodes
- Performed live migration of VM's across compute nodes during maintenance and failure.
- Doing BA/VA of cloud infrastructure for Security and hardening of cloud images.
- Implementing continuous Integration Jenkins tools to build and release cloud Images.
- Giving Technical support to customers for their application hosted on Cloud with 24/7 hours.

Project Name: Switch N walk, Jio Money, IOT, Easy Clinic, Jio Network (Feb 2015- Jan 2016)

Description: Building private cloud infrastructure for on boarding JIO OTT applications infrastructure like media, non-media, IOT, health services.

Environment: Openstack Cloud platform

Responsibilities:

- Building Projects with networks, subnets, routers, ports along with defined security groups
- Provisioned Instances, volumes, mapped security groups, associated floating IP's, load balancer, Virtual IP for failover cluster setup as per project design.
- Prepare Heat Template Projects Environments to replicate in Pre-PROD, PROD setup.
- Migrated Projects setup and applications across tenants and cloud with backup

- Closely Work with Mirantis to resolve control plane issues
- Performed Continuous delivery using docker, git, jenkins for application deployment
- Automated infra provisioning patch updates, package installation on instances using Ansible
- Automated Integrating Instances with security components like HPOM, PIM, VPN
- Automated daily routines in shell, PowerShell & shell scripts.
- Prepared unattended.xml file to automate prerequisites for windows instances
- Generating resource utilities for projects weekly basis based on ceilometer reports
- Building & troubleshooting windows servers failover cluster setup
- Scheduled backup of databases at regular intervals and maintained high availability.
- Performed Active directory management with failover cluster setup and applied group policies.
- Integrating system logs with HPOM, ZABBIX for monitoring and alerts
- Maintaining Instances with BA/VA complaint for cloud security and doing hardening
- 24/7 technical support to application owners and follows tickets

Project Name: Jio- Health Hub (Jan 2014 – Jan 2015)

Description: Professional Health services for all state governments. Jiohealthub for consumer health

application targeting to acquire 100 million clients.

Environment: AWS Cloud Platform

Responsibilities:

- Managing EC2, EBS, ELB, IAM, AMI, VPC and S3 bucket services, security groups.
- Deployed and configured web, Integration, cache servers and database for the services.
- Automated Continuous Integration and Continuous deployment with docker
- Managing Git and Jenkins configurations for users and team.
- Performed S3 migration from one Singapore to Mumbai region.
- Maintaining and fixing VA/BA complaint of servers to ensure its security
- Monitored the daily application functionality and parameter checks with Dev Team input.
- Installation and configuration of ZABBIX to monitor complete infrastructure and application.

Technical Skills:

- Automation Tools: GITlab, Jenkins, Maven, Ansible, Saltstack, Docker, Kubernetes, Terraform.
- Database: MySQL, MongoDB, SQL Server, MariaDB
- Application/Web Servers: Apache Tomcat
- Scripting: Bash Shell, Python
- Virtualization Technologies: Hyper-V, KVM, QEMU, Virtual Box
- Cloud Environments: Openstack, AWS
- Operating System: Linux (Redhat, Centos), Windows Desktop and server editions 2008/2008-R2/2012-R2, Ubuntu 14.04, 16.04, 18.04.
- **Storage:** GlusterFS, NFS, CephFS

Achievements

- Presented Paper "Monasca and 25,000+ Instances in Production User Story" at Openstack
 Summit 2019, Denver
- Presented Paper "Monasca- Monitoring as a service" at Opensource India 2018, Bangalore
- Presented Paper "Ceph Performance Tuning" at Openstack Summit 2016 at Barcelona

Educational Qualification

- B.E Electronics and communication (87.5 %) at Anna University, Chennai, Tamilnadu, India
- HSC (86 %) at Alagappa Matriculation Higher Secondary School, Karaikudi Tamilnadu, India
- SSLC (87%) at Alagappa Matriculation Higher Secondary School, Karaikudi Tamilnadu, India

Trainings & Certifications

- Completed Openstack Bootcamp I Training (OS 100) by Mirantis
- Completed Certified Openstack Administrator
- Certified of Cloud Security Knowledge (CCSK) by HP
- ITIL Certifications by HP